First off, thank you for the incredible support on my last video.
首先,感谢您对我最后的视频的令人难以置信的支持。
As we all know, things stay time.
正如我们都知道的那样,事情仍然是时间。
So today, I want to save you some time and jumpstart your cadeau journey with the lessons
所以今天,我想节省你一些时间,并用教训开始你的礼物之旅。
I wish I knew when I first started.
我希望我知道我什么时候开始了。
If I could go back and just tell myself 10 things about cadeau, I would have saved myself
如果我可以回来,只告诉自己关于礼物的10件事,我会拯救自己。
dozens of broken projects and a whole lot of frustration.
数十个破碎的项目和很多失望。
So today, I'm giving you everything I wish I knew before you even opened your door.
因此,今天,我把我希望我知道的一切都交给你,直到你打开了你的门。
I've been using the cadeau engine for more than 5 years now and I've watched it grow
我已经使用礼品发动机超过5年,现在我已经看到它成长了
from a niche tool into a powerhouse engine.
从一个尼切工具到一个发动机。
Even a huge game like Battlefield 6 uses it as the technology behind the community map
即使是一个巨大的游戏,如Battlefield 6使用它作为社区地图背后的技术。
editor and the portal creation toolkit that comes with the game as a level editor.
编辑器和门户创建工具套件,将游戏作为一个级别编辑器。
But when I first started, I had no idea what I was doing and honestly, the things I'm
但当我第一次开始时,我不知道我在做什么,坦率地说,我
about to share with you would have sped up my learning by months.
要和你分享,我的学习会延长几个月。
So whether you're brand new or just getting serious about cadeau in 2026, this video is
因此,无论你是新鲜的还是2026年的礼物,这段视频是
for you.
為你。
But before you even open your first cadeau project, let's talk about the biggest decision
但在你甚至打开你的第一个礼物项目之前,让我们谈谈最大的决定。
every beginner struggles with.
每个初学者都在争斗。
New devs always ask the same question, should I jump straight into the engine or do I need
新学者总是问同一个问题,我是否直接跳进发动机或我需要
to learn programming first?
首先要学习编程。
And here's the truth, if you already understand the basics of programming like what are
这里是真相,如果你已经理解编程的基本原理
variables, functions and loops, then yes, absolutely jump into cadeau.
变量,功能和跳跃,然后是的,绝对跳进礼物。
In fact, cadeau is designed to teach you as you build, but there's one thing you absolutely
事实上,礼物是为了教你你建造,但有一件事你绝对
must do first, get familiar with the cadeau docs.
首先,你必须熟悉礼物的礼物。
No really, hear me out, I know this seems boring, but go through the getting started section
不是真的,听我说,我知道这看起来很无聊,但走过开始的部分
in the official cadeau documentation.
在官方礼物文件中。
It's short, simple and teaches you the exact fundamentals cadeau expects you to know.
它是短暂的,简单的,教你正确的基本礼物等待你知道。
And make sure you do the example project.
并确保您完成示例项目。
Your first 2D game, if you're brand new to programming, then I suggest learning the basics
你的第一个2D游戏,如果你是新鲜的编程,那么我建议学习基本
first.
首先。
They're not a sponsor, but honestly, GD Quest has one of the best beginner friendly foundations
他们不是赞助商,但坦率地说,GD Quest拥有最好的初学友好的基础之一。
out there.
外面。
The learn GD script from zero course, it's free, it's clean, it's simple and made for
学习 GD 脚本从零课程,它是免费的,它是干净的,它是简单的,并为
total beginners.
全初学者
Now once you're comfortable inside the editor, there's one habit that can save your future
现在,一旦你在编辑器内部舒适,就有一种习惯可以拯救你的未来。
self so much pain.
自己有这么多痛苦
Let's talk about that next.
让我们谈谈下一个。
One of the biggest mistakes I made when I just started out was writing code that only
我刚刚开始写代码时犯下的最大的错误之一就是写代码。
I could understand and trust me, if you do this in 6 months, you won't understand it either.
我可以理解和信任我,如果你在6个月内做到这一点,你也不会明白。
To avoid that, always write readable code.
为了避免这一点,总是写出可读的代码。
Use clear variable names like player speed and not PS1.
使用清晰的变量名称,如播放器速度,而不是PS1。
Use descriptive function names like player movement instead of just movement and break
使用描述函数名称,如玩家运动,而不是只是移动和中断
big functions into smaller single purpose ones where practical.
大功能在较小的单个目的,在实用的地方。
Your goal is simple, write code today that future you can understand instantly because
你的目标是简单的,今天写代码,未来你可以立即理解,因为
readable code makes debugging so much easier, but even clean code won't help you if you
可阅读的代码使解密变得更容易,但即使清洁的代码也不会帮助你
don't know where to find answers.
不知道在哪里找到答案。
And GDOS has a massively underrated resource.
而且,GDOS有一个大规模低估的资源。
One of the best habits you can learn early is static typing.
早期学习的最佳习惯之一是静态打字。
This means telling GDOS what type of data a variable should have.
这意味着告诉GDOS什么类型的数据一个变量应该有。
Just like this, bar speed colon float equals 200.0.
类似于此,条速肠流量相当于200.0。
Instead of bar speed equal 200.0.
代替条速度相当于200.0。
Why this is matter?
為什麼這是問題?
Because GDOS will warn you about errors before you run the game.
因为GDOS在运行游戏之前会警告你错误。
It catches type mismatches, wrong arguments and a ton of subtle bugs you don't want to
它抓住类型的错误,错误的论点和你不想要的微妙的错误。
deal with later.
随后处理。
And here two more best practices every beginner should know.
这里有两个最好的做法,每个初学者都应该知道。
Don't put heavy logic in the process and physics process function.
不要把重的逻辑放在过程和物理过程功能中。
If something doesn't need to run every frame, don't put it in process or physics process
如果有些东西不需要运行每个框架,不要将其放入过程或物理过程。
that really slows things down.
这真的放缓了事情。
And can make debugging messy.
它可以使Messy的破碎。
Don't create super deep node hierarchies.
不要创建超深节点层。
Keep your scenes organized by grouping related things together.
保持您的场景安排,将相关事物聚集在一起。
The node tree is your architecture so use it wisely.
节点树是你的建筑,所以用它明智。
And if you ever want the official full list of best practices, here it is.
如果你想正式完整的最佳实践列表,这里是。
Alright, now let's get into the fun part.
好吧,现在,让我们走进有趣的部分。
These are 10 workflow shortcuts that completely changed how enjoyable GDOS is for me.
這是10個工作流短縮,完全改變了 GDOS 對我來說有多愉快。
Even if some of these don't make sense yet.
即使有些人还没有意义。
Just take notes and keep them in mind as you do your research.
只需留下笔记并记住它们,当你做你的研究。
Trust me, learning these will save you hours or even days later.
相信我,学习这些会节省你几个小时甚至几天后。
Tip 1.
提示1。
Learn signals early.
早点学习信号。
Signals are everywhere in GDOS.
信号在GDOS中到处都是。
And one of the reasons the engine is so flexible.
这是发动机如此灵活的原因之一。
Learn how to use them early.
学习如何提前使用它们。
This will make your life so much easier.
这将使你的生活更容易。
I personally wish I had spent more time on this when I first started.
我个人希望当我第一次开始时,我花了更多的时间。
Tip 2.
提示2。
Use separate scenes for reusable elements.
使用可重复使用的元素的单独场景。
Things like help bars, enemy bullets, or even a UI panel.
像帮助栏,敌人子弹,甚至一个UI面板等事情。
Make each of these its own scene.
让每个人都有自己的场景。
That way you can reuse it anywhere in your project without having to rebuild it every
这样你就可以在你的项目中的任何地方重新使用它,而无需重建它。
time.
时间。
Tip 3.
提示3。
Make Duplicated Nodes Unique.
使双重节点独特。
Whenever you duplicate a node, use the Make Unique option.
每当您重复一个节点时,请使用 Make Unique 选项。
If you don't, resources like collision shapes or scripts might be shared between nodes.
如果没有,资源如冲突形式或脚本可能会在节点之间共享。
And that can lead to really tricky bugs.
这可能会导致真正的麻烦错误。
Taking the simple steps saves so much headache.
采取简单的步骤会节省这么多头痛。
Tip 4.
提示4。
Keep Scenes Modular.
保持场景模块化。
Try to build small chunks instead of one giant scene.
试着建造小碎片而不是一个巨大的场景。
Modular scenes makes your game easier to manage, debug, and expand later.
模块化场景使您的游戏更容易管理,拆卸,并在以后扩展。
I learned this the hard way.
我以艰难的方式学到了这一点。
After making one too many massive messy scenes.
在做一个太多的巨大的混乱场景后。
Tip 5.
提示5。
Reuse Functions Across Scripts.
重复使用字体中的功能。
Whenever you have logics that is used more than once, put it in a helper script.
每当你有逻辑被使用多次,把它放在一个助手脚本。
Reusing Functions This way keeps your code cleaner and prevents you
重新使用功能 这样保持您的代码更干净,并防止您
from rewriting the same logic over and over.
从重写相同的逻辑一遍又一遍。
Tip 6.
提示6。
Learn Autolodes.
学习自动化。
The Singleton Pattern.
单曲模式。
Autolodes are perfect for global systems like scores, audio managers, or save data.
Autolodes 非常适合全球系统,如分数、音频管理器或数据存储。
Once you get comfortable with them, you'll wonder how you ever lived without them.
一旦你和他们舒服,你会想知道你曾经没有他们生活的样子。
Tip 7.
提示7。
Use Node Groups.
使用 Node 组。
Groups let you target multiple nodes at once.
团体允许您同时针对多个节点。
For example, you can target all doors or all ladders.
例如,您可以针对所有门或所有充电器。
Then you can send a single command and affect everything in that group.
然后,你可以发送一个单一的命令,并影响该组的一切。
It's a huge time saver.
这是一个巨大的节约时间。
Tip 8.
提示8。
Master the Animation Player node early.
早点掌握动画播放器节点。
Animation Player is not just for fancy animations.
动画播放器不仅仅是为了幻想动画。
It can control UI transitions, effects, and even gameplay sequences.
它可以控制UI过渡,效果,甚至游戏序列。
Once you understand it, it's one of the most powerful tools in Kado.
一旦你明白这一点,它是卡多最强大的工具之一。
Tip 9.
提示9。
Turn on Debug Options.
点击 Debug 选项。
Things like collision shapes, navigation, measures, and physics debugging are life savers.
碰撞形状、导航、测量和物理漏洞等事物是节省生命的。
I've spent hours hunting down bugs that I could have seen immediately by enabling these
我花了几个小时狩猎错误,我可以立即看到,通过允许这些
options early on.
早期选项
Tip 10.
提示10。
Use De Debugger and Profiler.
使用 Debugger 和 Profiler。
The Debugger and Profiler are there to catch problems before they even become nightmares.
Debugger 和 Profiler 在那里捕捉问题,直到它们甚至变成噩梦。
Most beginners don't even touch them, but I promise if you start using them, it will
大多数初学者甚至不会触摸它们,但我承诺如果你开始使用它们,它会
save you hours of trial and error.
节省了几个小时的尝试和错误。
And after all these steps, here's something everyone thinking about learning the dough and
而且,在所有这些步骤之后,这里是每个人都想到学习的东西。
game development in general should know.
游戏发展一般应该知道。
Now I have to be straight here.
现在我必须在这里直立。
Game development is just like any other skill.
游戏发展就像任何其他技能一样。
When you start, you don't know what you're doing, you don't know the techniques.
当你开始时,你不知道你在做什么,你不知道技术。
And you know what?
你知道什么?
That's okay.
这是好事。
The dough is improving fast.
气味正在快速改善。
Version 4.6 is already out, but don't wait for the perfect version.
版本 4.6 已经发布了,但不要等待完美的版本。
If you keep waiting for the next big release, then you know what?
如果你一直在等待下一个大释放,那么你知道什么?
You'll never start.
你永远不会开始。
The fastest way to learn is to start building small projects.
学习的最快方法是开始建造小项目。
Now, not your dream RPG.
现在,不是你的梦想RPG。
Make a platformer.
做一个平台。
It's up down shooter.
它是上下射击器。
A simple physics game or even a UI prototype.
一个简单的物理游戏,甚至一个UI原型。
Each small project teaches you something new.
每个小项目都会教你一些新的东西。
That's how you level up.
这就是你升级的方式。
And if you ever feel stuck, here's what you should do next.
如果你有时感到困惑,这里是你应该做的事情。
Follow these tips, subscribe and join in the discussion.
遵循这些提示,订阅并加入讨论。
That's how you can jumpstart your journey with Gadoo.
这就是你可以通过Gadoo开始你的旅程的方式。
If you like the video, smash that like button so the video reaches more people that may
如果你喜欢视频,打破它喜欢按钮,以便视频达到更多的人
need it.
需要它。
And I also want to hear from you.
我也想听从你。
Are you already using Gadoo or experimenting with AI in your workflow?
您是否已经使用 Gadoo 或在工作流中进行 AI 实验?
Drop a comment below and let's talk.
点击下面的评论,让我们谈谈。
I'll be checking the comments regularly and I read every single one and get back to
我会经常检查评论,我会读到每一个,然后回来。
you.
你。
Until next time, thanks for watching.
直到下次,谢谢你观看。
Happy coding.
快乐的编码
Keep experimenting and I'll see you in the comments.
继续尝试,我会在评论中见到你。
This has been The Raku Games.
这就是拉库游戏。